Finding Aid for Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures (University of Michigan) records 1966-1999
University of Michigan. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures.
1 linear foot
2010039
This collection contains administrative materials such as meeting minutes, departmental program information, correspondence and personnel files. A large bulk of the collection is dedicated to the numerous external and internal reviews of the department from 1975 to 1994. The collection also includes publications and publicity, as well as personal correspondence, and details relating to a visit by Joseph Brodsky.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Dept of Slavic Languages and Literatures in 2008 (Donor No. 10099
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The records of the Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures are currently entirely covered by the Executive Officers restriction.
Personnel Related Records -- Box 1
Executive Officer Records -- Box 1
The Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures sprang from the Department of Russian Languages and Literatures. This department was established in 1910 in response to a University Bulletin describing the need for such a department because of the growth of Russia as a global influence. Courses in Polish languages and literatures were soon added to the department in 1920, and in 1947 an official masters program in Russian was developed. By 1952 the department became officially known by its current name under the chairmanship of James O. Ferrell, and a masters program for all of the Slavic languages offered was created.
In 1957, Deming Brown took over as chairman of the department, and the following year a PhD program was officially adopted. The decade from 1961 to 1971 was a period of intense growth for the department, in response to the "post-Sputnik" era. It was shortly before this period that the National Defense Education Act was passed in 1958, which established the Slavic languages and literatures department as a Slavic and East European Languages Center in the early 1960s. This designation provided the department with federal funding and support for its language programs in Russian and Polish, as well as Czech, Serbo-Croatian and Ukrainian.
It was also during this time period that chairman John Mersereau and Professor Ladislav Matejka established Michigan Slavic Publications, which fostered academic work concerning Slavic languages and literature. Departmental publications and Russian works published by Ardis publishing, which was created by former professor Carl Proffer and his wife Ellendea, were key in drawing Nobel Laureate-to-be and recent USSR-exile Joseph Brodsky to the University of Michigan. He would later become a tenured professor in the program.
Since the 1960s, the department has maintained a partnership with the Russian and East European Studies (CREES) program, by providing instruction to undergraduates and graduate students, and hosting faculty from Russia, Ukraine, Poland, Czech Republic, Hungary and Romania. The department now focuses on Russian, but still offers broad coverage of non-Russian Slavic languages as well.
-------------------------------
Sources consulted
Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures website: http://www.lsa.umich.edu/slavic/about/history/
Shaw, Wilfred B. The Univeristy of Michigan: An Encyclopedia Survey
The Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures collection dates from 1966 to 1999, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1968 to 1994. The material in the collection came in one accession, and its original order was maintained as much as possible. Materials are grouped by the following series: Administrative, Miscellaneous and Publications and Publicity. Within these series, the original order was retained.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures.; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996.; Slavic countries -- Study and teaching
- Administrative
  The Administrative file dates from 1966 to 1999, with the bulk of the material falling into the 1968 to 1994 range. This series contains meeting minutes, departmental correspondence, materials relating to the external and internal departmental reviews, personnel files and information about the programs offered in the department.
  - Department, faculty and executive committee meeting minutes
    - 1990-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1985 (Box 1)
  - Executive committee assignments, 1962-1999 (Box 1)
  - Personnel
    - Curricula vitae (Box 1)
    - Dewey, Horace W., 1961-1992 (Box 1)
    - Eulogies (Deming Brown, Irwin Titunik, Carl Proffer) (Box 1)
    - Ferrell, James O., 1952-1989 (Box 1)
    - Harshanyi, Nicholae (Box 1)
    - Planning, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Program information, 1990-2003 (Box 1)
  - Reviews
    - 1994 External/Internal Review
      - Schedule (Box 1)
      - Charge (Box 1)
      - Internal Review document (Box 1)
      - Appendix D to Internal Review document (Box 1)
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - Reviewers' vitae (Box 1)
      - External report (Box 1)
      - Unit reply (Box 1)
    - External Review, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Linguistics Internal Review, 1980 (Box 1)
    - College Priorities Committee Program Evaluation Committee Report, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Program Review
      - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
      - 1973-1974(2) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Departmental, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Personnel, 1968-1990 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous file dates from 1996 and 1987. This series contains information about a planned visit by Joseph Brodsky that was turned into a commemoration conference when he passed away before the event. Also included is a personal letter from faculty Assya Humesky.
  - Isaac Emmanuilovich Babel Centenary Exhibition and Symposium, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Patricia Bateman Campus Disruptions, 1968 (Box 1)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2043; removed to vault storage]
  - Joseph Brodsky visit/commemoration, 1996 (includes photo of Brodsky) (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence, 1987 (Box 1)
- Publications and Publicity
  The Publications and Publicity dates from 1975 to 2007. This series contains the Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures newsletter Slavic Scene, as well as clipping and posters related to the department's programs, and a paper by faculty Benjamin Stolz, which is undated.
  - Publicity
    - Clippings, brochures and posters, 1975-1993 (Box 1)
  - Publications
    - Papers (Box 1)
    - Slavic Scene newsletter, 1991-2007 (Box 1)